# Tom Blain

I am interested in working in the data science and machine learning field. I have strong skills implementing ML algorithms in Python, with experience in both Bayesian and frequentist inference and a solid foundation in mathematical and statistical principles. I am passionate about using machine learning approaches to solve real-world problems, with a focus on developing and applying advanced ML algorithms to drive real world change.

Proficient in Python, R, JAGS, C#, LATEX

Skilled in Pandas, Scikit-learn, PyTorch

Experience applying machine learning to a breadth of data science tasks, such as computer vision, natural language processing and big data.

#### **EDUCATION**

## University of Bristol

Sept 2019 - Jun 2023

MSci in Mathematics [2:1]

Relevant units including Markov Chain Monte Carlo Methods, Data Science, Bayesian Modelling, Theory of Inference, Artificial Intelligence, Mathematical Programming, Stochastic Optimisation, Statistics and Probability, Complex Networks, Multivariate Analysis.

## PREVIOUS PROJECTS

Previous projects are available to view on my data science portfolio

#### Masters Thesis: Advancements in Variational Inference

Sept 2022 - May 2023

- · Large literature review surrounding variational inference, an optimisation based method for finding an approximation for a posterior.
- · Topics contained including Adaptive learning rate gradient descent and variance reduction methods for GD, Reparameterization trick and automatic differentiation.

# Brain tumor MRI detection (Python)

March - May 2023

- · CNN model to detect and identify brain tumors from MRI images, with a focus on scalability.
- · GPU parallelization via processing mini batches, model checkpointing, efficient pytorch data structures with data loaders. ResNet50 and VGG16 deep convolutional networks for image recognition.

## IMDb Rating Prediction (Python)

Jan - Feb 2023

- · Creating a database using BeautifulSoup web scraper and IMDb API requests.
- · Encoding actor data, pre-trained transformer embedding for plot and title, LDA topic allocation, XGBoost regression model.
- · Additional personal project: Variational Autoencoder to generate realistic movie plots.

# Porto Seguro's Safe Driver Prediction (Python/R) - Kaggle

Oct - Dec 2022

- · Bayesian optimization of LightGBM boosting algorithm to predict probability of driver filing an insurance claim
- · Exploratory data analysis to deal with difficult to interpret data.

## Automatic Playlist Continuation on the Spotify platform (Python)

Jan - Apr 2022

- · Extracting features from a large dataset using Spotify API and NLP vectors.
- ANNOY Approximate Nearest Neighbours Model with an angular distance metric. Generates playlist of song recommendations based on input playlist.

#### Code Breaking with Statistical Physics (Python)

Jan - May 2021

- · Analysing frequency of n-grams in various languages
- · Metropolis-Hastings MCMC Algorithm to solve difficult given ciphers

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Airbus Oct 2018 - Jan 2019

· Designing and developing an AI system for frequency allocation with a professional team.

House of Lords Nov 2018

· Participating in a discussion on the future of cybersecurity in the modern world led by industry professionals.

BAE systems

Jun - Jul 2019

· Taking part in a work experience scheme with the cybersecurity department.

## PREVIOUS ROLES

Front of house Jun - Nov 2021

· Worked with an acclaimed chef to design a social enterprise community supermarket to support local producers, funds for the project are being raised from selling a restaurant cookbook which I helped edit and photograph. As the only member of the waiting team, I improved my design making under pressure and gained valuable skills communicating with guests.

# Supercell/The Diana Award Youth Board

2016-2019

· Working closely with charity The Diana Award, I visited Helsinki on numerous occasions to work with popular gaming company Supercell on safety measures for children in the online world. During this role I also worked with MP's to promote UK wide anti-bullying campaigns, and worked with Facebook as part of a small focus group launching a national campaign with aims to decrease online bullying on Facebook platforms.

A level Mathematics (A\*), Further Mathematics (A) and Computer Science (A)